Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is דף ל"ו, Daf
Lamed Vuv, and we pick up with in the middle of ה'
עמוד ב'. Hey Amud Beis. We're dealing with the idea that on
חול המועד Chol Hamoed you can mark graves and different הלכות Halachos
about things that need to be marked. And we pick up where
it says there's a little אלף Aleph in the middle about a
third of the way down, and we're two lines above that where
it says ואלו הן הספקות. Ve'elu Hein Hasfekos. סככות ופרעות. Skhochohs Upraohts.
The following things that's considered doubtful things that need to be marked
because things that everybody knows and that's obvious does not need to
be marked. So the following things are doubtful that need to be
marked. No we did not. סככות
אילן המיסך על הארץ. Skhochohs Ilan Hameisakh Al Haaretz. סככות Skhochohs are
is a tree that overhangs and is like bordered at a layout
that you would, that you know, where you assume that somebody would
have buried a body under, but there's a doubt, is a body
definitely buried under it? Is there, does the טומאה Tumah definitely communicate
it to this branch? Under which branch is the body buried? And
ופרעות Upraohts is similarly אבנים פרועות היוצאות מן הגדר, Avonim Pruos Hayotsos
Min Hageder, so like outcropping of rocks from a wall and also
that they can communicate טומאה, Tumah, but you have to know that
there's something only if something is buried there and it doesn't always,
you'd have to know whether, you know, under which space is it
buried and under where is there a problem?
Now בית הפרס, Beis Hapras,
what's a בית הפרס? Beis Hapras? כדתנן, Kidisnon, like we've learned there
is החורש את הקבר הרי הוא עושה בית הפרס. Hachoreish Es Hakever
Harei Hu Oseh Beis Hapras. If somebody plows over a grave, not
intentionally one would hope, then the entire area's a בית הפרס Beis
Hapras because there might be little bits of bone or whatever spread
throughout and therefore you don't exactly know where it is, so since
there's enough areas to be doubtful about, it's only a rabbinic problem,
but rabbinically you cannot go or a כהן Kohein cannot go in
that whole field. And if you go you're טמא, Tamei, but it's
all ספק. Safek. וכמה הוא עושה Vekamah Hu Oseh and how much
of a space if you plowed over the grave is it considered
to be the area could become a בית הפרס? Beis Hapras? מלא
מענה מאה אמה. Melo Ma'anah Meiah Amah. A length of a hundred
אמה Amah which is long, you know, whatever 150 feet, but for
the width of a מענה Ma'anah which is the plow that you
would have plowed over with so it could extend the entire width
of the plow but for a hundred אמות. Amos. ובית הפרס מי
מטמא באוהל Uveis Hapras Mimitamei Baohel the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
we've agreed that the only time that you do a marking is
if it's מטמא באוהל Mitamei Baohel because you could walk over it
without the wearing it if it's something that you could see on
the ground, you would not be concerned, but a בית הפרס Beis
Hapras is only a concern of scattered bones on the ground. It's
not a concern of אוהל. Ohel. ובית הפרס מי מטמא באוהל Uveis
Hapras Mimitamei Baohel is it really causes טומאה באוהל? Tumah Baohel? ואמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל מנפח אדם בית הפרס והולך. Veamar Rav Yehuda
Amar Shmuel Menafeiach Adam Beis Hapras Veholeikh. You can blow your, you
know like with your from with your mouth, you can blow the
area right in front of you, it's like clearing a minefield, you
know you blow the area right in front of you so you
scatter any debris that's right in front of you, you take a
step. Then you blow and you take a step. So the only
concern of בית Beis and that would allow you to walk through
a בית הפרס. Beis Hapras. So the only concern of בית הפרס
Beis Hapras are things that are on the surface, not things that
are below. רב יהודה בר אמי משמיה דעולא אמר בית הפרס שנידש
טהור. Rav Yehuda Bar Ammi Mishmei D'Ulla Amar Beis Hapras Shenidash Tahor.
If you have a בית הפרס Beis Hapras that's been trampled, people
have walked through after it became a בית הפרס Beis Hapras and
made a path just through walking through, then that path is okay
because any, you know, little remnants would have been already kicked away
or pushed under the ground. So you see that it's not a
only concern of what's from the surface and we said that we
don't do markings when it's on the surface. Now of course the
difference could obviously be that normal things we would only be concerned
about באוהל. Baohel. Here where the concern is tiny little pieces of
bone even if it's not באוהל, Baohel, it's not things that people
will obviously see and we can't just assume that you'll see it
yourself. That to me is the most obvious answer that you know
as a rule the only we're only concerned about אוהל Ohel because
otherwise things are visible, but if the concern here is tiny little
pieces of bones that scatter around, you know then then why should
we be concerned? I mean then we need to mark it. However
the ברייתא Braisa did say that we don't even mark pieces of
bone that are the small size of a שעורה, Seorah, a small
size of a barley bean. So it was pretty clear that even
tiny things we don't mark unless it's מטמא באוהל. Mitamei Baohel. So
it's not clear why we have to feel we have to mark
the בית הפרס. Beis Hapras. Yes.
Actually this entire discussion is
concerning כבוד המת Kevod Hameis and stuff like that.
Even on יום טוב Yom Tov is there issue?
So if you saw those things you'd have to bury them.
Even on, but putting on like a sign like whatever it is,
oh mark
this is חול המועד.
Chol Hamoed. I know, but what would be the problem doing it
on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
What do you mean? תובע? Toveia?
No, not, not, maybe if you had a sign you just like
put it.
All right, I don't know, we'd have to figure out if that's
bone or not. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. I
don't know, Michael, this is not a הלכה שיעור. Halacha Shiur. So
the גמרא Gemara says you'd bury it if you saw it. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, אמר פפא, Amara Papa,
so what do you do if you don't, why should you have
to mark it if it's all only a concern of what's on
the surface and not אוהל? Ohel? So אמר פפא לא קשיא כאן
בשדה שעבר בה קבר כאן בשדה. Amar Papa Lo Kashya Kan Besadeh
She'avar Bah Kever Kan Besadeh. נחרש בה קבר. necherash ba kever. There
are two types of בית הפרס. beis hapras. בית הפרס beis hapras
is used for plowing over, that's normal use, but it's also used
to describe a field in which there's a body buried and you
don't know where, you forgot where the body was buried. In that
case, the concern is what is under the ground and is a
concern of אהל, ohel, and that's the case where you need to
make a marker on the field. So now the גמרא Gemara says
ושדה, v'sadeh, the גר"א'ס Gra's which is the גרסה, girsa, because the
גמרא Gemara takes for granted that a plowed field is
a בית הפרס. beis hapras. The חידוש chidush here is that even
a field where a grave cannot be identified is a בית הפרס.
beis hapras. So the גר"א Gra switches the גרסה girsa to say
the following: ושדה שאבד בה קבר בית הפרס קרי ליה? v'sadeh she'avad
ba kever beis hapras kari lei?
What, just because you've lost the grave in the field, you don't
know where the grave is, you're going to call that a בית
הפרס? beis hapras? That's not our classic בית הפרס. beis hapras. גמרא
Gemara says אין, in, yes, that's what. We have a משנה. Mishnah.
שלשה בית הפרסין, shlosha beis haprasin, there are three things that are
called a בית הפרס. beis hapras. שדה שנאבד בה קבר, sadeh shene'evad
ba kever, a field that a grave is lost in it, you
don't know where it is, ושדה שנחרש בה קבר, v'sadeh shenecherash ba
kever, and a field that has a grave plowed over, ושדה בוכין,
v'sdei bochin,
and a field of crying. Now, by the way, the גר"א Gra
says the original גרסה girsa is כוכין. kuchin. A כוך kuch is
a little, what do they call, ossuary, like the, is that what
it's called? The thing in the graves, where in the caves where
they would bury... Is that an ossuary? Yeah, where they were in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that's where they would bury the bodies. But
our גרסה girsa is שדה בוכין, sdei bochin, a field of crying.
So מאי שדה בוכין, mai sdei bochin, what is a field of
crying? רב יהושע בר אבא משמיה דעולא אמר: Rav Yehoshua bar Abba
mishmei d'Ulla amar: שדה שמפטירין בה מתים, sadeh she'maftirin bah meisim, the
field in which you take leave of the dead. The way the
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom explains it is, you're carrying the dead from
one city to bury in another city. You get to a certain
field and you do the handoff. The people from the city, you
know, that he originally came from, hands off to the people that
are taking him and gonna go bury him. And therefore everybody stops
and does their final like, you know, הספדים hespedim and crying and
so on. So that's why it's a שדה בוכין. sdei bochin. So
what's the concern? Why do we think that that there might be
טומאה tumah there? They're doing a handoff. So the גמרא Gemara says
וטעמא מאי, v'taama mai,
and what is the reason why it's considered a בית הפרס beis
hapras and there's a doubtful טומאה? tumah? אמר אבימי, amar Avimi, משום
יאוש בעלים נגעו בה, mishum yei'ush ba'alim nag'u bah,
because of the sort of despair of the owners. Now what does
that mean? So it could mean that, you know, that somehow, I
don't know, you know, they handed it off and then all of
a sudden it became a downpour or whatever, and the people of
the other city said, "Oh, let's go for cover, we'll come back
and we'll get the מת meis later," and then they forgot about
it, or something like that. רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom doesn't want to
say it's that drastic. He says maybe like a little piece of
the מת meis fell off and they forgot about it. Of course
I don't know if it's in a coffin, how is a little
piece falling off and why would it דוקא davka fall off there?
Anyway, somehow because they're doing a handoff there, you're afraid that something
got lost in that field, a part or part of the body,
and it's a בית הפרס. beis hapras.
Or maybe because, yeah, when was the מנהג minhag that they used
to like bury for a year and then when the corpse decomposed,
they took the bones and they buried it in the...
so you mean they forgot to move the
bones, in the ancestral thing and then when they move it, you
know, that's how some piece of bone falls.
Could be, could be, that's an interesting thought. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: ושדה שנחרש בה קבר לא בעי ציוּם? v'sadeh
shenecherash ba kever lo ba'ei ziyum? Are you telling me that if
it's plowed over it doesn't need a marker? Because like as I
said, you know, it would seem you would need a marker, you
know, just like the whole point is the whole field is off
limits even though nothing looks wrong with it. And now we're going
to bring a proof. דתניא, de'tanya, we learned a ברייתא braisa in
the תוספתא, Tosefta, מצא שדה מצוינת, matza sadeh metzuyenet, you found an
excellent field, no, a designated field. A field with a marker. ואין
ידוע מה טיבה, v'ein yadu'a mah tiva, and you don't know what
type of a field this is, why it's being marked. Is it
a field that has a קבר kever lost in it, or is
it a field that has a קבר kever plowed over? Now why
do you care? Because we just taught that if it has a
קבר kever plowed over, you can clear a path for yourself, you
can blow in front of yourself every step and clear a path.
So you want to know what type of problematic field this is,
and all you see is an indiscriminate marker.
יש בה אילנות בידוע שנחרש בה קבר, yesh bah ilanos, bi'ydu'a shenecherash
ba kever, if it has trees, then you know that it's a
field that has been plowed over. אין בה אילנות בידוע שאבד בה
קבר, ein bah ilanos, bi'ydu'a she'avad ba kever, if it doesn't have
trees,
you know that a קבר kever has been lost, or you have
to suspect a קבר kever has been lost and therefore you cannot.
Now why should trees matter? So רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says that
if it's got, if it has trees, that means that it's, that
you had to plow it in order to plant the trees. So
therefore you have the concern of נחרש בה קבר. necherash ba kever.
Of course that's funny because it doesn't mean definitely נחרש, necherash, you
could also be אבד. avad. So anyway תוספות Tosfos gives a, I
mean it was definitely נחרש, necherash, but it doesn't mean the קבר
kever itself was plowed over. תוספות Tosfos gives a different answer. He
quotes a תוספתא Tosefta that says that if a field has a
קבר kever lost in it, you're not allowed to plant the field.
So in that scenario, you imagine that in one case, you knew
there was a קבר, kever, you plowed the field because you wanted
to plant, and and you wanted or whatever, not just you're not
allowed to plant, but you're not allowed to plant in it. So
in one case, you know, you knew there was a קבר. kever.
So fine, there's a קבר. kever. You can plant, you know where
the קבר kever is. There's no concern that it'll be obscured. And
then of course what happened over time, the קבר, kever, people forgot.
Take a look at those what's the ברייתא Beraita, *brayta*? דתניא detanya,
*detanya* התם *hasham* תוספתא *Tosefta* says, שדה שאבד בה קבר kever *sadeh
she’avad bah
kever*, I got it
I got it right. If a grave is lost, אינה ניטעת כל
נטע *einah nita’at kol neta*. Okay, then you don't plant. I got
it right. So there’s a הלכה *halacha* that you’re not allowed to
plant a field that a grave is lost in, maybe to mark
that a grave is lost or maybe because once you’re planting it,
there’s even less likelihood that you’re ever going to be able to
dig up and find where the קבר kever, *kever* is. Maybe benefit
of kever? Maybe. Okay, so that’s תוספתא *Tosefta*’s view. So in that
case, let’s take a look again.
So if
יש בה אילנות *yesh bah ilanot*, if it has trees, בידוע שנחרש
בה קבר kever. *biyadu’a shenechrash bah kever*. So the only reasonable scenario
is not that the grave was lost, then you wouldn’t be able
to plant trees, but you knew there was a grave there and
therefore you planted trees and then accidentally it got plowed over and
it became a בית הפרס beis hapras *beit hapras* that way. אין
בה אילנות *ein bah ilanot*, if there are no trees, בידוע שאבד
בה קבר kever *biyadu’a she’avad bah kever*, you’re following the הלכה *halacha*
and we assume that the grave is lost. So in the case
when there is trees, you’re allowed to walk there because we assume
that it’s only a בית הפרס beis hapras *beit hapras*, a בית
הפרס beis hapras *beit hapras* of plowing and therefore you can walk
by blowing in front of you. ר' יהודה אומר *Rebbe Yehuda omer*
עד שיש שם זקן או תלמיד *ad sheyesh sham zaken o talmid*,
until there’s an elder or a student, and a student presumably will
mean a rabbinic student, דמפני שאינו כל בקי בדבר *d’mifnei she’eino kol
baki b’davar*, not everybody is expert, meaning A, not everybody is expert
presumably meaning that you can’t ask the normal person, you have to
ask an elder or a rabbinic student who would more pay attention
to those things, but B, he’s also saying that you can’t necessarily
make right derivations from the fact of whether there are trees or
not trees. You have to that’s not enough evidence. Anyway, what you
see here regardless is that you could have a marked field that
might be one of the two types
of בית הפרס *beit hapras*. But we’ve been saying that you don’t
mark a field that has a grave plowed over, you only mark
a field that has a lost grave. So what’s the story? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa, *Amar
Rav Pappa* כי תניא היא בשדה שאבד בה קבר kever *ki tanya
hi besadeh she’avad bah kever*. No, here’s the scenario: you only mark
a field that has a grave lost in it. So that’s the
way it started. No question, there was a grave lost and you
marked it. דציינוה *detziyanuh* and you marked it. So it started that
way as a field that had a grave lost. Now, יש בה
אילנות *yesh bah ilanot*, if there are now trees, בידוע שנחרש בה
קבר *biyadu’a shenechrash bah kever*. So now that's an evidence that the
grave that was lost has now been presumably, I don't know, found
and plowed over and that's why they were allowed to plant trees,
because it was no longer a grave that was lost. אין בה
אילנות *ein bah ilanot*, if there's no trees, בידוע שאבד בה קבר
*biyadu’a she’avad bah kever*. So you know that it was lost and
it was not plowed over. So it's I gotta tell you, it's
a very strange well, the answer isn't strange, but if you stop
and think about it, it's hard, at least for me, to fully
unpack this, which is, he says, look, first of all, to me
it seems that the better answer is that why not mark a
בית הפרס *beit hapras* even though it's not מטמא באהל *metameh b’ohel*
for the reasons I've been saying, it might not be מטמא באהל
*metameh b’ohel* but it's very easy for you to become טמא tamei.
*tamei* and not to see what you're stepping on. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s insisting that if it was the case of a בית
הפרס *beit hapras* where it was plowed over and it was all
on the surface and not buried, you wouldn't mark it. So we've
got the problem that we've got this ברייתא Baraisa *brayta* that says
that you have a marked field and you don't know what type
of a בית הפרס *beit hapras* it is, whereas you only mark
one type. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying yeah, you only mark
one type, but type A can transform into type B. It started
as a field that has a grave lost and you marked it,
and now maybe what happened was after that, it got plowed over,
maybe they plowed over the entire field. So the field that was
the grave that was lost has now stopped being a grave that
was lost and has become the other type of a בית הפרס
*beit hapras* where it's been plowed over and it's scattered throughout the
field. So that's how you can get a case where it was
marked even though it'll be the type B בית הפרס *beit hapras*
because it started as A and it transformed to B. So okay,
on one level that's simple enough, but logically there's a problem because
when it becomes the type B בית הפרס *beit hapras* of plowed
over, it becomes more lenient, right? It becomes more lenient in the
sense that you only have to worry about the
surface, you don't have to worry about what's buried, okay? And therefore
you can like blow your way through it, blow your way through
it. But if that's true, why can we assume, right, if it
started with the more problematic one, how can we assume that it
completely transformed to the other one and completely, you know, removed all
the pre-existing problems of the more problematic one? Meaning do we know
that the grave was completely plowed and everything got surfaced? And I
just don't really fully understand how come that type of if it
started with one and it maybe got plowed over, even if it
did get plowed over, how it completely removed the problems of the
previous type of a בית הפרס *beit hapras*. But anyway, be that
as it may, that's our answer. Our answer is that we would
only mark it if it was lost, but this could have started
that way and transformed. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אין באילנות בידוע שאבד בקבר, Ein b'ilanos biyadu'a she'avad bakever, so if
there's no trees you then you know because of the rule that
you don't plant if the field is lost, then you know that
the grave I mean if the grave was lost, that the grave
was lost. So the גמרא Gemara says ודלמא שתיל מאילנות מגואי וקבר
מבראי, V'dilma shteil me'ilanos migavai v'kever mibarai, so let's say there are
trees. So you say oh there are trees, good, it's the better
בית הפרס you can blow your way through it because it's just
plowed over. So the גמרא Gemara says but I don't get it,
maybe the trees are on the interior and the קבר is on
the exterior? And therefore the tree area might not have a lost
קבר, but outside of the trees might have a lost קבר. So
the גמרא Gemara says כדאמר עולא בעומדין על הגבולין, K'd'amar Ulla b'omdin
al hagvulin, so like עולא Ulla says in a similar or another
context when you're right at the border, הכא נמי בעומדין על הגבולין,
Hacha nami b'omdin al hagvulin, here too you're right on the border,
which basically means the way רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says it is
that the trees are right at the border of רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, so you're not going to plant a קבר in רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. So therefore they're not outside of the border, the trees,
any קבר would be inside the trees. And therefore if it's inside
the trees, it would not be a case of a lost grave
as we said because where there are trees you're not concerned of
a lost grave because the rule is you don't plant where there's
a lost grave and it's only concerned of the plowed over grave.
So the גמרא Gemara says top of ו עמוד א, Vav Amud
Aleph, ודלמא טומאה מגואי ואילנות מבראי, V'dilma tumah migavai v'ilanos mibarai, so
okay say the reverse though.
Here you are, you've got your trees,
and the גמרא gemara says so you've got your trees, here's your
field like that's marked. So the גמרא gemara says well okay there
are trees there but maybe the טומאה tumah is over here? No,
no, no, this is a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Nobody's planting in
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay, it says, but let's even have some
more trees, right? But maybe there's an area in here on the
interior that has no trees? And that's the place where there's the
lost grave. So again how can you still assume that there's no
lost
grave,
maybe the trees are on the outside and the grave is on
the inside? So the גמרא gemara says במסובכין. B'mesubachin. No, the trees
are all interspersed, they're spread throughout the entire field, there is no
place that there's no trees. And therefore if the whole thing is
scattered with trees, it's only the בית הפרס of the surface, not
the בית הפרס of something buried. And therefore you can blow your
way through it. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima, if you want you could
say הא דאמרן אין מרחיקין ציון ממקום טומאה שלא להפסיד את ארץ
ישראל, Ha d'amran ein marchikin tziyun mimkom tumah shelo l'hafsid es Eretz
Yisrael, you do not distance the marker from the place of טומאה
tumah not to cause the loss of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Right,
you have the marker right at the edge of where the טומאה
tumah is. So if your markers are here, we're going to see
by the way a marker is not three dimensional, it's whatever, everything's
three dimensional in this world but anyway, but it's basically a white
strip
on the surface of the ground. So if here's where your markers
are then you can't say oh but maybe maybe the טומאה tumah
is in here, right? And this is still, you know, and this
is the place where there's you know a buried טומאה tumah because
there are no trees here. No, if the טומאה tumah was in
here you would have put the markers at the edges of the
field. If you're putting the markers at the edges of the field,
right, then that means that the טומאה tumah because then you would
have put your marker more interior, so you don't distance the marker
from where the טומאה tumah is. Okay, so therefore in that you
don't have to be you can assume that the טומאה tumah is
in the area which is juxtaposed to the marker and therefore and
not in some other area.
And it's only in there and it's a field of trees. Exactly.
And so how you going to get way through, there's an אהל
ohel thing from the branches?
Well but again we're assuming that because there's trees there's no buried
טומאה, tumah, it's all on the surface and it's all broken up
and they're pieces that are not big enough to cause טומאה באהל.
tumah b'ohel. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says, עד שישם זקן או תלמיד, Ad sheyeishem zaken o talmid,
until there's an elder or a student, לפי שאין הכל בקיאין בדבר,
L'fi she'ein hakol beki'in badavar, not everybody is an expert, which means
a, you have to ask, and b, you can only ask these
people presumably these types of people. אמר אביי שמע מינה צורבא מרבנן
דאיתא במתא, Amar Abaye shma mina tzurva merabanan d'isa b'masa, we hear
from this that if there's a student of the rabbis in a
city, so you know guy learning in ישיבה, yeshiva, כל מילי דמתא
עליה רמי, Kol mili d'masa alei rami, he has to pay attention
to all the dealings of the city because he's the one that's
responsible for things that go on in the city. So that's what
I've always found that every all the people that are in ישיבה
yeshiva they really take a serious interest in local city politics and
they have to know everything that's going on because they know they're
responsible for everything in the city. All right. אמר רב יהודה, Amar
Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says, מצא אבן מצויינת, Matza even
metzuyenes, now if you find a marked stone, so basically like there's
you know some whitewash on the stone, so תחתיה טמא, tachteha tamei,
directly underneath it is טמא. tamei. Now we have a little bit
of a problem because we said that the marker is supposed to
be before you encounter the טומאה. tumah. But the רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom here says that it's because it's raised and it's three dimensional
you see it from a distance. The reason we say it has
to be it has to be not directly on but but you
know before the טומאה, tumah, like I said the other day of
like the yellow line before you know the subway track, so you
keep your distance before you get right there. But if it's three
dimensional you see it from a distance, you won't be get on
top of it until before it's too late. Okay
so therefore. If you see the stone marks, directly underneath it is
טומאה. tumah. It's not marking off a three-dimensional area, it's just marking
its I mean you know an area, two-dimensional area, it's just marking
its own space.
שתים, אם יש חורש ביניהם ביניהם טהור. Shtayim im yesh choresh benehem
benehem tahor. If it's plowed between them, going back to some of
these issues before about plowing and whatever. Did I skip a line?
Yes, I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
אם יש סיד ביניהם ביניהם טמא. Im yesh sid benehem benehem tamei.
If there's plaster between them, so
between them is טמא. tamei? ואם אין סיד ביניהם ביניהם טהור. Ve'im
ein sid benehem benehem tahor. And if not, then between them is
טהור. tahor. So you basically have in the middle of some field,
you've got two stones. Here are your two stones and there's plaster,
somebody put some white plaster, okay, so put some white plaster on
it. Okay, so underneath each one stone you'd say under it there's
a טומאה. tumah. Two stones, would you say under this is a
טומאה tumah and under this is a טומאה? tumah? Would you say
that they're demarcating the whole space between them as well and that
that whole space is טמא? tamei. So it says only if the
plaster is actually on this space or the whitewash, you have to
assume the space between them is טמא. tamei. Otherwise, you only assume
directly underneath them is
טמא. tamei. ביניהם ביניהם טהור. Benehem benehem tahor. אף על גב דליכא
חורש. Af al gav delika choresh. The גמרא Gemara says even if
there is nothing plowed, you can assume the space between them is
טהור tahor if it's only on the two stones. ותניא, Vetanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, Baraisa מצא
אבן אחת מצויינת תחתיה טמא. Matza even achat metzuyenet tachteha tamei. If
you found one stone marked, underneath it is טמא. tamei. שתים Shtayim,
אם יש חורש ביניהם ביניהם טהור. Im yesh choresh benehem benehem tahor.
If there are two, then if the area between them is plowed,
it's טהור. tahor. ואם לאו ביניהם טמא. Ve'im lav benehem tamei. If
not, it's טמא. tamei. So it sounds like even without plaster, that's
not enough, it needs to be plowed, going back to some of
the issues before that plowing is some indication of things being better.
That it needs to be plowed in order to assume that the
space between them is okay. So how do you reconcile these ברייתות?
Beraitot? So אמר רב
פפא, הכא כשהסיד שופך על גביהם ומרודד לכאן ולכאן. Hacha keshehasid shofech
al gabeihem umerudad lechan ulechan. The case is you have plaster,
you don't have obvious plaster
that is all the way there. You've got plaster, you still plaster
on the top of the stone or whatever, this white, whatever it
is, this whitewash, and some of it spills like, okay, this is
what it looks like and you see like some of this. So
the obvious question you want to ask yourself is what's going on
here? Was this initially a whole strip that was marked and the
space between here somehow got, you know, worn away? Or were they
just marking the stones and some of the plaster spilled over a
little bit? Okay, and that's the scenario where you'll determine it based
on whether the area between it is plowed. Okay, so that's the
case. אי איכא חורש ביניהם ביניהם טהור. Ei ika choresh benehem benehem
tahor. If it was plowed between them, then the space between is
טהור. tahor. Why?
דאימא מחמת חורש הוא דאיכסו. De'eima mechamat choresh hu de'ichsu. Because then
you would say that really there was no initial, initial markings here,
you know, maybe or maybe there was like a little bit over
here like this, a little fell on the ground, but then you
came through with your plow and that sort of turned over the
dirt here and got some of these markings to like move into
that zone. So then you have to say that then you'll say
that the original area wasn't marked at all and it was because
of the חורש choresh that it looks a little marked and therefore
it's really טהור. tahor. ואי
לאו סידא דביני וביני הוא וטמא. Ve'ei lav sida de'veini uveini hu
vetamei. But if it's not planted,
then you'll say if it was not planted and even so it's
sort of it's going at somewhat of a distance,
then you'll say that okay, that really shows that they meant to
mark the distant area and the area in between them and therefore
between them is טמא. tamei, Again, logically I would have said the
exact opposite, but okay. Moving on. The תוספות Tosafot tries to explain
it differently. Clearly I do not understand enough of what's going on
here in terms of the מציאות metziut that they are describing. But
moving on.
Okay. ואמר רבי אסי, Ve'amar Rabbi Assi, מצד מצר אחד מצויין, Mitzad
metzar echad metzuyan, if you have one boundary of a field designated,
marked, הוא טמא וכל השדה כולה טהורה. Hu tamei vechol hasadeh kullah
tehorah. Then it's just underneath that boundary is טמא, tamei. but the
whole field is טהור. tahor. שתים הן טמאים וכל השדה כולה טהורה.
Shtayim hen tmeim vechol hasadeh kullah tehorah. If you have two boundaries,
only them, you don't assume it's marking the whole field. שלשה, Shloshah,
three boundaries, now normally if three boundaries are marked, I would think
it's marking the whole field. No. הן טמאים וכל השדה כולה טהורה.
Hen tmeim vechol hasadeh kullah tehorah. Only they themselves. ארבעה, Arba'ah, only
when all four boundaries of the field are marked, הן טהורין. hen
tehorin. Then they're considered to be marking the field at a distance,
not just marking themselves, וכל השדה כולה טמאה, vechol hasadeh kullah tme'ah,
and the whole field is טמא. tamei. דאמר מר ארחוקי ציון ממקום
טומאה שלא להפסיד ארץ ישראל. De'amar mar archuki tziyun mimkom tumah shelo
lehafssid Eretz Yisrael. You do not distance it, so it's not exactly
clear what this is proving, but what it's proving is that the,
that you do distance it somewhat. You don't distance it too far,
but you distance it somewhat, so that case the actual place of
the marking is טהור, tahor, but the field in between is טמא.
Okay, so that's the end at least for now of this discussion
of marking the graves, again a little confusing because right here he's
talking about marking the field, right? We're talking about not. three-dimensional. We're
talking about marking the ground, and even though we're marking the ground,
if you only have one, two, or three of them, you say
directly underneath, so you get back to the old problem, but maybe
you'll be stepping on it and it's too late before you realized
it. So there definitely are some things here that are not being
fully unpacked and explained. For me, as I said, the thing that's
most problematic is how a once a something that begins as אובד
בקבר oved bakever can get upgraded and less problematic because it's נחרש.
nechrash. I don't really fully understand that yet.
Yes. It's my images of the field and mass, or mass graves,
Europe.
Yeah.
About, yeah, the fact that you've got these large fields. Right. Right,
I mean, here ברוך השם baruch hashem those weren't the scenarios. It
was a large field but there was one grave. But, yeah, but,
yeah, you're right. Okay, and now we get to the next, the
final part of the משנה mishnah that lists what you do on
חול המועד, chol hamoed, these things that are sort of important for
the general welfare, whether that religious or physical welfare. And יוצאין אף
על הכלאים. yotsin af al hakilayim. Here's another one that's about their
religious welfare until because all the earlier stuff had been more about
their, well, מקואות mikvaot was sort of religious as well. Anyway, but
most of it had been about their sort of economic and here
we're getting to the religious. So one was the graves, and you
also send out messengers to take care of people that might have
כלאים kilayim growing in their fields. So let's take a look.
והכלאים בחול המועד נפקינן. vahakilayim bechol hamoed nafkinan. What, you wait till
חול המועד chol hamoed to send them out? ורמינהי uremini I'll ask
you.
באחד באדר משמיעין על השקלים. beachad be'adar mashmiin al hashkalim. You make
an announcement that people are going to start having to give their
שקלים, shkalim, right? You collect it so that by ראש חודש ניסן
rosh chodesh nisan you have all new communal funds to buy the
קרבנות korbanot from. ועל הכלאים, ve'al hakilayim, and people just have to
be careful because it's beginning to be the time where, you know,
things begin are beginning to sprout forth in the ניסן nisan period,
the אדר adar and the ניסן, nisan, and you'll see if accidentally
there's כלאים kilayim growing in your field.
בחמישה עשר בו קורין את המגילה בכרכין. bechamishah asar bo korin et
ham'gillah bikrachin. You read the מגילה m'gillah in walled cities. ויוצאין veyotsin
and then that's when you send out people to take care of
a lot of these public issues. ולקוץ את הדרכים ulekotz et hadrachim
to remove the, you know, the sharp objects in the roads. ולתקן
את הרחובות uletaken et harechovot to fix up like the dirt paths
that might have gotten, you know, damaged. ולמוד המקואות ulamod hamikvaot to
measure the מקואות mikvaot that maybe, you know, again during the previous
season, the rainy season, things have gotten... well, rainy season could be
good, but it could also cause mud and things to fall and
might have ruined the מקואות. mikvaot. You measure them, make sure there's
enough water in them. ועושין כל צורכי רבים veosin kol tzorchei rabbim
you do all the needs of the רבים. rabbim. ומציינין את הקברות
umetzaynin et hakevarot you mark the graves, again, you were just at
the pre... you're just coming out of the rainy season, that could
have gotten washed away. ויוצאין על הכלאים veyotsin al hakilayim and you
go out on the כלאים. kilayim. So גמרא Gemara says look, you've
already done it a month ago. Why would you be doing it
on חול המועד? chol hamoed? Now, why do you think it didn't
ask about everything else? Right? You... so everything in the משנה mishnah
that it said you do on חול המועד, chol hamoed, fix up
the roads, measure the מקואות, mikvaot, it should have said, you did
all of that a month ago on the 15th of אדר. adar.
So what's the answer?
That this stuff, right? You ever spend an hour cleaning up and
then five minutes later you gotta clean up again? Okay. A lot
of this stuff doesn't get just done once. You fixed the road
a month ago, maybe you gotta fix it again, right? Especially because,
you know, a lot of these stuff you might have to do
a second or third time. But the גמרא Gemara says בכלאים bakilayim
if you uprooted all the כלאים kilayim that's growing, you fixed the
problem. People aren't planting new yet at this stage. So why... so
all this other stuff you have to do twice, you might have
to do again, but why do you have to do כלאים kilayim
in חול המועד? chol hamoed? So that's the thing the answer's going
to be. But first let's understand why it's just asking about the
כלאים. kilayim. So גמרא Gemara. says רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי בר חנינא.
Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Yossi bar Hanina. חד אמר כאן בבכיר וכאן באפיל.
Chad amar kahn bevachir vekahn be'afil. Exactly like I said, there's early
growing stuff and late growing stuff. So you get out, you go
in the 15th of אדר adar to take care of the early
stuff, and then you later take care of the late stuff. Of
course, the question is why not just go out on the late
stuff, but it's an important issue and you want to be on
top of it. Okay. וחד אמר כאן בזרעים וכאן בירקות. Vechad amar
kahn bizraim vekahn beyerakot. It's one is talking about seeds, meaning like
grain, and that's... and the other and then it's vegetables, vegetables start
becoming a, you know, start sprouting later, so we go twice. All
right. אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi
Yochanan. לא שנו אלא שאין ניצן ניכר. Lo shanu ela she'ein nitzan
nikar. This idea that you don't do anything about it prior to
like the 15th of אדר, adar, this is the way רבינו גרשום
Rabbeinu Gershom reads it, is only if their sprouting is not yet
evident beforehand. אבל ניצן ניכר יוצאין עליהם. Aval nitzan nikar yotsin aleihen.
But once their sprouting is evident, if it happens to be a
year that the stuff is sprouting forth earlier, then you're going to
go out earlier. It's not like an absolute earliest time is the
15th of אדר, adar, that's just the standard time. Okay. מאי שנא
בחולו של מועד דנפקינן? Mai shna becholos shel moed dnafkinan? To now,
okay, given that, you know, we went out a month ago, why,
if we're... we accept that we have to do it more than
once, but why pick חול המועד chol hamoed to go out? Now,
this is different than why doesn't it ask about everything else, because
everything else could be that the problem is, you know, came up
around now, right? Right around... the street was fine, but in the
last two three days over יום טוב yom tov the street... it
got ruined or the מקוה Mikvah got ruined or whatever it is,
you know maybe something came up that you gotta take care of
on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. But the כלאים Kilayim you could have
easily planned for that before יום טוב Yom Tov or after יום
טוב, Yom Tov, right? It's not like it's something happened just now.
So why did we wait for חול המועד Chol HaMoed to take
care of the כלאים? Kilayim? Why דווקא davka during חול המועד? Chol
HaMoed? So,
אמר רב יעקב אמר רב יוחנן משום שכר פעולה דמוזלי גביה. Amar
Rav Yaakov, Amar Rav Yochanan, mishum sechar pe'ulah de'mozli gaba. Fascinating answer,
you know why? Cause cause labor is cheap on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. You know why labor is cheap? Cause they're not allow cause
no, cause they're not allowed to work on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
So you're not allowed to work on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, so
labor is cheap. Now of course, are we allowed to do this?
So why are you allowed to do this? So one reason might
be, you know, this is צרכי מצוה tzorchei mitzvah that overrides, or
we're going to find other places that for people that they can't
make a living and really need to work just to basically, you
know, put food on the table, there are special allowances for חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. But the basic point is pretty much everybody's off
of work on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So labor is cheap. I
would say everyone went on עליה לרגל.
aliya laregel. Maybe.
אמר רב זביד ואיתימא, Amar Rav Zvid ve'isayma, but you don't just
do it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, אמר רב
זביד ואיתימא, Amar Rav Zvid
ve'isayma, anyway it's not דווקא davka בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אמר רב
זביד ואיתימא רב משרשיא, Amar Rav Zvid ve'isayma Rav Mesharshaya, שמע מינה,
shema mina, we can infer from that,
כי יהבינן להו שכר מתרומת הלשכה יהבינן להו ki yahavinan lehu sechar
mi'trumas halishka yahavinan lehu when we pay the people that go out
for כלאים, Kilayim, we pay them from not only from, you know,
from communal funds and he's specifically saying the תרומת הלשכה, Trumas HaLishka,
the money that we're raising, you know, every year, the money we
raise every year around אדר Adar time is A, for קרבנות, korbanos,
but not just for קרבנות korbanos as we learned when we learned
שקלים, Shekalim, sometimes it's other types of communal funds, which is a
whole interesting question because it's sanctified but you're using it for non-sanctified
purposes, communal purposes but not sanctified and that gives is the issue
about בית דין beis din's right to stipulate what the money's going
to be used for. But anyway, we're using it from these communal
funds that we've collected and therefore we want to get a good
deal. What's the alternative? The alternative is you could make who who
could you make pay for? The owners of the field that had
כלאים, Kilayim, they'll be the ones that get fined and have to
pay for their, you know, you know, for the cost of sending
these people out. So in that case, who who needs to make
it cheap? Let them be more expensive, let them get fined even
more. So the גמרא Gemara says, דאי סלקא דעתך מדידהו יהבינן להו,
di'i salka daitach mididehu yahavinan lehu, if we pay them from from
their funds, meaning the funds of the owners of the fields, so
מאי נפקא לן מינייהו, mai nafka lanei minaihu, what difference do we
care that we want to make make it get it at a
cheap time? כל כמה דבעו ליטפו להו, kol kama deba'u liseun lehu,
כל
כמה דבעו ליטפו להו, kol kama deba'u liseun lehu, however much they
need they should pay. So therefore clearly you see it's coming from
the communal funds. Why we don't make it the other thing, I
don't know, it probably also could be given to a little bit
too much corruption if you direct that the owner has to pay,
cause then they'll be too eager to find כלאים Kilayim maybe where
there isn't כלאים, Kilayim, who knows? ועד כמה, Ve'ad kama, how much
of a mixture of seeds is considered כלאים? Kilayim? Like if you
get a few stray seeds mixed up, does that make it כלאים?
Kilayim? So אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Shmuel Bar
Rav Yitzchak, כאותה ששנינו, ke'osa sheshanim, like we taught in כלאים, Kilayim,
כל סאה שיש בה רובע, kol se'ah sheyesh bah rova, any סאה
se'ah that has in it a רובע rova of a קב, kav,
which is that one to twenty-four proportion, so it's a little bit
more than four percent, זרע ממין אחר zera mimin acher from a
different type of a seed, ימעט, yema'et, you have to lower the
distribution, meaning you have a whole big mixture of your your wheat
seed and accidentally a little bit of I don't know some bag
of, you know, of something else, of some grain seed accidentally opened
up and got mixed in, right? Do you have to throw it
all out? So as long as you lower the mixture to be
less than one to twenty-four, it's no longer considered כלאים Kilayim and
you can plant it.
Right, a couple times. What is it? I think there's a couple
reasons why you do it out of the תרומת הלשכה, Trumas HaLishka,
let's say they're out a whole day and for some reason they
find no כלאים. Kilayim. Right. That's also.
Right. That's also.
And another thing is, you know, the owner may not have ready
money and this person needs to be.
Okay, those are also good, those are good points as well. Correct.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, והתניא, ve'hatanya, now,
התקינו שיהו מפקירים כל השדה כולה, hiskinu shehu mafkirin kol hasadeh kullah,
we taught in a ברייתא Baraisa, that they would sort of, you
know, seize the entire field. So it would not just be that
they would be ימעט, mema'et, that they would lower the distribution, solve
the כלאים Kilayim problem. It sounds like in a ברייתא braita: that
they would completely, you know, it's like this rule that they have,
right, about, you know, vehicles that are found in, you know, they
seize like the a vehicle that's involved in a crimes, right? That's
why they always have the police, you know, auctions of seized vehicles.
Anyway, so if the field was involved in a crime, they could
seize the field. So the entire field gets taken. It's not just
that they fix the problem and minimize the כלאים. Kilayim. So what?
Impounding. Impounding, exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult. כאן קודם תקנה כאן לאחר תקנה. kan kodem takanah,
kan achar takanah. There were two stages in this, before and after.
What are the two stages? דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא, braita.
בראשונה היו עוקרים ומשליכים לפני בהמתן. barishonah hayu okerim umashlichim lifnei behemton.
By originally the the messengers would go out and they'd find כלאים
Kilayim and they'd uproot it, root it, and throw the stuff that
was growing, the foreign stuff, in front of the animals. of the
farmers, of the people of the field. והיו בעלי בתים שמחים, Ve-hayu
baalei batim smeichim, the owners would be thrilled. שתי שמחות, Shtei smachot,
two things. אחת שמנכשים להם שדותיהם, Achat she-menachshim lahem sadoteihem, thank you
very much for weeding my field, ואחת שמשליכים לפני בהמתם, ve-achat she-mashlichim
lifnei behemtam, and thank you very much for feeding my animals. So
which also shows you by the way that it's not that people
are intentionally planting כלאים, kilayim, or at least not most of the
time, but they're just not being careful enough, right? So they basically
they don't who wants to plant wheat with I don't know with
you know eggplant in the middle? You're just not being careful enough
to sort out your seeds. So then somebody comes and takes care
of the problem for you, wonderful, you'll take care of the problem.
It actually encourages less care because somebody else is going to have
to deal with it. So okay, so התקינו שיהיו עוקרים ומשליכים על
הדרכים. Hitkinu she-yihyu okrim u-mashlichim al ha-drachim. Then they said okay fine
we'll uproot it and they'll throw it on the roads. ועדיין היו
שמחים שמחה גדולה שמנכשים שדותיהם. Ve-adayin hayu smeichim simcha gedola she-menachshim sadoteihem.
They're still thrilled, thank you very much for coming and weeding my
field, getting rid of the foreign stuff.
התקינו שיהיו מפקירים כל השדה כולה. Hitkinu she-yihyu mafkirim kol ha-sadeh kullah.
Then we had to make a real consequence. Okay, if you're growing
כלאים, kilayim, your whole field is going to be seized. All right,
so that's going out on כלאים. kilayim. Now we move to the
next משנה mishna continuing things you can and cannot do on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov
omer, מושכין את המים מאילן לאילן ובלבד שלא ישקה את כל השדה.
moshkin et ha-mayim me-ilan le-ilan u-belvad she-lo yashkeh et kol ha-sadeh. You
can draw the water from one tree to the next, but you
cannot draw the water for the rest of the field. We're assuming
that the rest of the field is a בית הבעל, beit ha-baal,
a field that is that the rainwater is sufficient, is not in
need of irrigation, and therefore it's again this problem that it is
not a case of הפסד hefsed for the rest of the field.
זרעים שלא שתו לפני המועד לא ישקם במועד. Zraim she-lo shatu lifnei
ha-moed lo yashkeim ba-moed. Seeds that have not been watered before the
מועד moed cannot be watered on the מועד moed because again if
they haven't that's a case where they're not in desperate need. It's
a little ironic, you'd say wow if they haven't been watered before
they need to be watered, but the thinking is if they haven't
been watered before it's because they're not in need of watering. So
therefore you can't all of a sudden wake up and say oh
maybe I'll water them on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. No, the things
you water on חול המועד Chol HaMoed are things that are in
regular need of watering. So if this hasn't been watered before, it's
not in regular need is the assumption and you don't water on
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. וחכמים מתירים בזה ובזה. Va-chachamim matirim be-zeh u-ve-zeh.
But the חכמים chachamim allow both cases. Now that's a little bit
strange. Either it's a debate of designating is this considered הפסד hefsed
or not הפסד hefsed because we could debate the facts. Maybe they
think those cases are considered to be הפסד. hefsed. But assume they're
not debating the facts, it seems that these חכמים chachamim are what
we learned in an earlier דף, daf, a position of רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that you're allowed to
water even a בית הבעל beit ha-baal on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed,
even a case where it's not a הפסד, hefsed, just a case
of making sure you get the full benefit of the field, not
losing a potential profit, even that is allowed for רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. And that makes sense because חכמים chachamim is often רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Okay, so this might be the position of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that is much more liberal and that allows you to
do things that are even when there's not a הפסד hefsed on
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda,
if היתה שדה מתוננת, haita sadeh metunenet, if it's a field that
is מתוננת, metunenet, which is an interesting word but basically it's understood
to be a word that means that it was a moist field
but then it dried up, okay? So it's sort of like a
so it's again a case of like הפסד. hefsed. In that case
מותר, mutar, it is permissible. That's a case of הפסד. hefsed. Even
if it had been a בית הבעל, beit ha-baal, it's now really
dried up and in desperate need of water, it's permissible. תניא נמי
הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly. כששנו אסור להשקותם במועד, Keshe-shanu
assur le-hashkotam ba-moed, when they said that you can't water things on
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, לא אמרו אלא בזרעים שלא שתו לפני המועד.
lo amru ella bi-zraim she-lo shatu lifnei ha-moed. That's only things that
have not been watered beforehand, which again presumably means is not in
regular need of watering. אבל זרעים ששתו לפני המועד מותר להשקותם במועד.
Aval zraim she-shatu lifnei ha-moed mutar le-hashkotam ba-moed. But if they had
been watered before and they're in regular need, then they can be
watered on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. וגם היתה שדה מתוננת, Ve-gam haita
sadeh metunenet, again if this field that's מתוננת, metunenet, which presumably means
a field that maybe didn't generally need water, you know, was sort
of very rich and moist soil but dried up, in that case
מותר, mutar, it is allowed. Okay. ואין משקין שדה גריד במועד. Ve-ein
mashkin sadeh gerid ba-moed. You do not water a dried field on
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, meaning not one that dried up but one
that's always dry, because that again is a field that either watering
it won't do it any good or doesn't really survives on very
little water, so that field you cannot do. וחכמים מתירים בזה ובזה.
Va-chachamim matirim be-zeh u-ve-zeh. And the חכמים chachamim allow this and this.
Again both of those cases, presumably it's not a case of הפסד,
hefsed, but again like the חכמים chachamim we saw in the משנה,
mishna, חכמים chachamim don't need it to be a הפסד. hefsed. We'll
read the גמרא Gemara that way and therefore they allow it even
though it's not a הפסד, hefsed, even if it's just to prevent
loss of profit. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, שמע מינה, shma mina, we
can infer from this. Now there's a major debate in the ראשונים
rishonim what is he referring to? הרא"ש, The Rosh,
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom reads it and the רש"י Rashi on the
רי"ף, Riff, גירסא היא, girsa hi, שמע מינה shma mina or the
רי"ף Riff says. שמע מינה מדרבנן. Shma mina mid'rabbanan. We can infer
from the rabbis, meaning from the חכמים. Chachamim. Why is that important?
Because the big question is, how do we פסקן? pasken? So we
פסקן pasken like what until now has been the סתם משנה, stam
mishna, which has been the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that there has
to be a הפסד, hefsed, or maybe we פסקן pasken like רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who's much more liberal, who says you can do
this type of stuff even if it's just about not having a
loss of profit, right? So if
רבינא Ravina is saying שמע מינה מדרבנן, shma mina mid'rabbanan, we infer
from the חכמים, chachamim, then he's actually implicitly פסקנינג paskening and he's
going to tell you פסק הלכה, psak halacha, he's פסקנינג paskening like
the חכמים. chachamim. That's the way some ראשונים Rishonim read it. Let's
read it that way. אמר רבינא Amar Ravina שמע מינה, shma mina,
we can infer from this last statement that בזה ובזה מותר, bezeh
u'vezeh mutar, that האי תרביצא, hai tarbitza, if you have a תרביצא
tarbitza which is basically like a garden, a vegetable garden, so שרי
לתרבוציה בחולו של מועדא. shari l'tarbutzeh be'cholo shel moada. You can water
it on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Why? Because even though not watering
it would not be a loss, but you're allowed to water things
even to allow a greater gain, even to allow... and how do
you know that? Because he says סדי גריד מאי טעמא, sadi grid
mai ta'ama, why by a סדי גריד sadi grid are you allowed
to water it according to the חכמים, Chachamim, even though it's a
very dry field, it's not in desperate and it doesn't like, it's
didn't dry up, it doesn't need water right now? So why are
you allowed to water it? דאפלא משוי ליה חרפא, de'afala mashvei leh
charpa, because this is stuff that would grow late, but by watering
it you're going to make it grow early. So therefore, and nevertheless
you're allowed to do it to increase the profit. הכא נמי אפלא
משוי ליה חרפא. hacha nami afala mashvei leh charpa. Here too, by
a garden, you can water it even though anyway it'll grow later,
you can water it now so it'll grow earlier, and that's allowed.
So you read the גמרא Gemara, this way and it's a big
היתר heter on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. You can do stuff in
the field that's going to allow for an increased profit, or not
to have a loss of profit, and it's פסקנינג paskening like רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Other ראשונים Rishonim read this גמרא Gemara very differently.
First he says you're allowed to do it on חול המועד, Chol
HaMoed, and then the גמרא Gemara. challenges him, and the גמרא Gemara
says how can you say you're allowed to do it on חול
המועד? Chol HaMoed? You're not allowed... not that you're allowed to do
a סדי גריד, sadi grid, you're not allowed to do a סדי
גריד sadi grid just to increase profit. So how can you do
this to increase profit? And basically it's rejecting his position and going
back to the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So there's a...
this is a very contested line in the גמרא, Gemara which is
the question do we rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you can
only do it in a case of loss, or do we rule
like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you can even do it for the
sake of profit? Because they say when the גמרא Gemara says, it
doesn't say סדי גריד מאי טעמא sadi grid mai ta'ama as a
proof to him, it's a challenge to him. סדי גריד מאי טעמא
לא. sadi grid mai ta'ama lo. It's sort of like מאי טעמא
לא mai ta'ama lo is essentially why is it you're not allowed
to do a סדי גריד? sadi grid? Because you can't increase profit.
Well, here too it's increasing profit so you shouldn't be allowed to
do it. Okay, so this is a very contested line in the
גמרא. Gemara. There's a lot of גרסא girsa questions. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, our rabbis taught: מרביצין שדי לבן בשביעית. Marbitzin sdei lavan b'shvi'it.
You can water a wheat field on שביעית. shvi'it. מרביצין... Marbitzin... there's
a question whether that means... that might not mean normal watering, it
might mean like sprinkling, like or a mist, a small amount of
watering. That's also debated. But you can water a wheat field on
שביעית, shvi'it, אבל לא במועד, aval lo b'moed, not on חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. Okay, again, ironically we're being more lenient sometimes on שמיטה
shmita than on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. And again, you know, why
would we allow it at all? Watering a field on שמיטה? shmita?
Isn't that exactly what's biblically prohibited? So again, the גמרא gives two
explanations: either שמיטה shmita nowadays is דרבנן, d'rabbanan, or that what do
you call it, or things that are not explicitly in the תורה
Torah about שמיטה shmita are דרבנן, d'rabbanan, and watering is not explicitly
in the תורה. Torah. Okay, nevertheless it's quite funny because this seems
to be a case of ריוח, revach, not a case of הפסד.
hefsed. So some want to say that we're talking just about like
sprinkling water, not a serious watering of the field. Okay, but you
cannot do it on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. והתניא, Ve'hatanya, we turned
in a ברייתא: braita מרביצין בין במועד בין בשביעית. Marbitzin bein b'moed
bein b'shvi'it. You can do it in either. אמר רב הונא לא
קשיא, Amar Rav Huna lo kashya, so this is exactly the debate.
הא רבי אלעזר בן יעקב הא רבנן. Ha Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
ha Rabbanan. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov is the
one in our משנה mishna as we saw in the תנא קמא,
tanna kamma, the previous משנה, mishna, that does not allows much less
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, only when there's a real הפסד, hefsed,
so he won't allow it in both... he won't allow it on
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, that's the first ברייתא. braita: Whereas the second
ברייתא braita that allows it on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, that's the
רבנן, Rabbanan, that's the חכמים, Chachamim, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
allows things even for the sake of profit on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. Okay, so that's the debate of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. But
the interesting thing is, but everybody agrees on שמיטה shmita it's allowed.
So even a case which is now being implicitly designated as profit,
not as loss, and because it's profit they debate חול המועד, Chol
HaMoed, they agree you're allowed to do it on שמיטה. shmita. Again,
very strange, and the גמרא does not unpack why that would be
the case.
Okay. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we turned in another ברייתא: מרביצין שדי
לבן ערב שביעית. Marbitzin sdei lavan erev shvi'it. Now this ברייתא helps
us to get a little bit of a handle of why it's
allowed on שמיטה. shmita. You can go ahead and sprinkle whatever, water,
on a
wheat field ערב שביעית erev shvi'it כדי שיצאו ירקות בשביעית. kedei sheyetz'u
yerakot b'shvi'it. If it's ערב שביעית, erev shvi'it, you can do it
even for the sake that stuff will grow on שמיטה. shmita. Now
that sounds a little bit against the issues we spoke about before
about תוספת שביעית, tosefet shvi'it, right? A month before, months before, but
again maybe... maybe this is just a light watering and therefore it's
not seen as so major, that we allow even if it's for
the sake of stuff to grow on שמיטה. Shmita. But ולא עוד
v'lo od and this gets to the allowance we just
gave אלא שמרביצין שדי לבן בשביעית, ella she'marbitzin s'dei lavan b'shvi'is, you
can even do it on בשביעית, b'shvi'is, but here at least there's
a
qualification כדי שיצא ירקות למוצאי שביעית, kedei she'yeizei yarakas l'motzei shvi'is, not
to get stuff to grow now but to get stuff to grow
after שמיטה. Shmita. So at least it gives a little bit of
an explanation of why we're allowing it. But again the question should
raise: so I don't I get it, you can do any work
you want in the field on שמיטה Shmita if it's for the
sake of after שמיטה? Shmita? But again, you know, there's light work,
there's heavy work, there's work that's explicitly mentioned in the פסוקים, psukim,
there's this watering which is not explicitly mentioned in the פסוקים, psukim,
but at least this gives you a little bit of a handle
about why we were allowing it by שמיטה. Shmita. Let's take a
look now at the next משנה. mishna. Wow, we are catching up.
צדין את האישות ואת העכברים משדה האילן ומשדה הלבן כדרכו במועד ובשביעית.
tadin et ha'ishut v'et ha'achbarim mis'dei ha'ilan umis'dei halavan k'darko b'moed uv'shvi'is.
You can lay traps, you can capture an אישות, ishut, which is
like weasels, and עכברים, achbarim, which are rats from a—yeah, but some
say that's what an אישות ishut is or something like a weasel—from
a grain field or from a—I'm sorry—from a from an orchard or
from a grain field the normal way on חול המועד Chol Hamoed
and שביעית, Shvi'is, okay, because that's really considered an issue of הפסד.
hefsed. תוספות Tosafos raises the question: why do you even have to
discuss שמיטה? Shmita? Again, you're not working the field, you're just trapping;
I mean, okay, you're you're protecting the crops by trapping animals, but
you're not working the field, it's not even an issue to begin
with. He says, well, maybe in order to lay the trap you
have to remove—you know, you have to dig some stuff up and
you have to move boulders. But again, it is interesting that—and we
had that issue before about like digging a ditch for for bringing
water on שמיטה, Shmita, where the גמרא said: what should the problem
be? You're not working the field, you're just moving water, right? I
mean, when you dig in the ground, that's not working a field
if it's not a field. So anyway, it's something similar here. But
anyway, so it's not clear why שביעית Shvi'is should have even begun
to be a problem, but you can do both of them because
it's clearly a case of הפסד. hefsed. וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, but
the חכמים chachamim say—and this is interesting, because if it's the same
חכמים, chachamim, חכמים chachamim have usually been lenient and here they're going
to be strict. So if you look at the side, the other
גרסה girsa is רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, so at least
we're consistent that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the more stricter voice,
okay? So anyway, the other opinion is משדה האילן כדרכו ומשדה הלבן
שלא כדרכו: mis'dei ha'ilan k'darko umis'dei halavan she'lo k'darko: an orchard you
can do it normally, that's a serious הפסד; hefsed; a wheat field
you have to do a little bit of a שינוי. shinuy. Why?
Because apparently it's not such a הפסד. hefsed. The point is, okay,
it might not be such a הפסד, hefsed, but it's a הפסד.
hefsed. So again, it's not like they say don't do it, they
say do it a little with a שינוי. shinuy. ומקפיזין את הפירצה
במועד, umakpizin et hapirtza b'moed, you can you can basically seal over
a break in a fence on חול המועד Chol Hamoed ובשביעית בונה
כדרכו, uv'shvi'is boneh k'darko, and on שביעית Shvi'is you can even make
a fence initially. And that's interesting because one of the things you're
not allowed to do by שמיטה—you Shmita could say, well, you're not
working the field, you're just protecting it—but דווקא davka one of the
things you're not supposed to do on שמיטה Shmita is to do
actions that show that you're like expressing your own ownership or exerting
your ownership over your crops. So you might say building a fence—well,
a fence might keep out weasels and deer and other things, but
it also might keep out other people, right? So there is a
חידוש chidush there that you can build a fence on שמיטה, Shmita,
not because of the working of the field, but because of the
issues of ownership. Anyway, these things are allowed; these are issues related
to הפסד. hefsed. We have the stricter voice here, the חכמים, chachamim,
but we have normally been hearing the חכמים chachamim as the lenient
voice, so some have that גרסה girsa as רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. מאי אישות? Mai ishut? What
is this אישות ishut that you're trying to trap? אמר רב יהודה
בריה דבירי—excuse Amar Rav Yehuda b'rei d'Birei
me—שאין לה עיניים, she'ein lah einayim, it's a
it's some type of a creature without eyes, mole, like a mole.
Right, weasels have eyes, a mole, okay.
So אמר רבא בר ישמעאל ואיתימא רבי יימר בר שלמיא, Amar Rava
bar Yishmael v'eima Rabbi Yemer bar Shmaya, מאי קרא? mai kra? Where
do you see this in a פסוק? pasuk? כמו שבלול תמס יהלך,
k'mo shavlul temas yahalech, like שבלול—how shavlul does it translate שבלול shavlul
there? What's a שבלול? shavlul? I forgot to look it up.
Looks like a snail, right?
Snail. Okay. Like a snail that like loses its shell, like, you
know, will will melt away and go away. So נפל אשת בל
חזו שמש: nefel ashat bal chazu shamesh: will fall the
אישות, ishut, the אשת ashat that has not seen the sun. So
you see this thing called the אישות ishut doesn't see, it's a
mole. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Snail is the שבלול. shavlul. תנו רבנן:
Tanu rabanan: צדין את האישות ואת העכברים משדה הלבן ומשדה האילן כדרכו,
tadin et ha'ishut v'et ha'achbarim mis'dei halavan umis'dei ha'ilan k'darko, like the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of our משנה, mishna, you can trap for
this this these moles and rats from the from the wheat field
and from a orchard the normal way. ומחריבין חורי נמלים, umacharivin chorei
nemalim, and you can
destroy ant ant hills. Ant hills, have you ever seen those things?
They have a—like the Bronx Zoo, they've got these ant hills that
are like, you know, ten feet tall or something. Those are termite
mounds? Oh, my mistake. Okay, anyway, the ant hills—so ants don't make
hills on top? It's only down in the ground? They don't make
little hills?
They don't make termite mounds? Okay, fine. Anyway, you can destroy you
can destroy the holes of ants as well. כיצד מחריבין? keitzad macharivin?
How do you do that? How do How do you destroy the
anthills? So that's true, like ant farms, it's all underground, anyway, how
do you destroy the anthills? So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר *Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer*, מביא עפר מחור זה ונותן לתוך חור זה
*meivi afar mechur zeh venoten letoch chur zeh*, וחונקין זה את זה
*vechonkin zeh et zeh*. So basically he says that if you get
dirt from another ant's, ant's, ant farm, anthill, and you transfer dirt,
that'll cause them to like, to strangle them with the smell of
the other dirt. That's at least what רבינו גרשום *Rabbeinu Gershom* says,
the smell of the other dirt. I thought it meant he brings
some ants with the dirt and then they have like some some
wars or something, I don't know. Anyway, אמר רב יימר בר שלמיא
משמיה דאביי *Amar Rav Yeimar bar Shalamia mishmei d'Abaye*, והוא דקאי בתרי
עברי נהרא *vehu dekai bitrei evrei nahara*, it only works if they're
really distant, like you know anthills, there are two separate sides of
a river, והוא דליכא גישרא *vehu delika gishra*, and there's no way
to get from one side of the river to the next, there's
no there's no bridge, והוא דליכא גמלא *vehu delika gamla*, and there's
also not like a walk bridge, not a major bridge, והוא דליכא
מצרא *vehu delika metzra*, there's not even like a single plank bridge.
There's no nothing that lets you get from one side, I guess
the ants get from one side to the other side of the
river, and maybe people because they bring the dirt with them, so
you have to be really distant, different areas of earth, ועד כמה
*ve'ad kama*, also how distant do they have to be, עד פרסה
*ad parsa*, it has to be at least a פרסה *parsa* away
from one another and only then will this trick work to destroy
the anthills. Now you know.
Okay.